an entire book called Barry Solder and
the Magician's Rock, all about child
wizards. Let's build an AI agent to
write an entire book from scratch. Now,
I'm not talking about a short report or
like a children's book. I'm talking
about an entire novel from start to
finish in any genre that you can
imagine. By the end of this video, we'll
have an entire book that's 10 chapters
long, has an entire story arc from start
to finish, and is hopefully actually
enjoyable to read.
You simply input a book title and a
genre, and it completely does everything
else for you. To do this, we're going to
use an automation tool called Mind
Studio, the sponsor of today's video.
Now, before we totally dive into the
step-by-step process of how to build
this thing, I do want to make a quick
disclaimer. I don't actually think
people should completely write books
this way. If anything, you can use
something like this to create the first
draft, and then you should probably read
through it and add your own human touch
to it. But I still think there's
something kind of special about a book
that we know a human poured their heart
and soul into. I don't know if we'll
feel that same love from a book that we
know AI wrote for us, at least not for a
while. So, this video is designed to
demonstrate what an AI agent workflow
could be and to ideally get your wheels
spinning on what you can create yourself
with this technology. It's not meant to
be a tutorial on how to put AI slot
books out into the world. So, like I
mentioned, we're going to use Mind
Studio to build this. If you're not
familiar with Mind Studio, it's this AI
automation workflow with like these
nodes, and each of these nodes could
connect to like a different AI model.
So, you can have a node where somebody
inputs some text, and then the next node
goes and talks to Perplexity and has
Perplexity give information based on the
earlier inputed text, and then it could
go to another node and use GPT5, and
then another node and use clot if you
want. So, it's a really cool way to
build this sort of linear workflow that
could branch off into different areas
and every step in the workflow could
sort of tap a different AI model. I'm
going to head over to mine studio.ai
here. I'm going to click on my
workspace. I'm already logged in here.
If you don't have an account, go ahead
and uh create one and log in. And I'm
going to build a new agent. When we get
in here, we can see that we basically
just have a start node and an end node.
There's really nothing in between yet.
What we need to do to build out this
automation is start adding all of our
little nodes in between. I'm going to
actually delete the end node for now and
we'll add it back in later. But we do
need to collect some text input. I want
the user to give a title and a genre for
what this book is going to be about. And
then also an optional description. We're
going to use some logic. So if they
leave the description blank, AI will
write a description of the book for
them. And if they write their own
description, then it will use the
description they wrote to sort of write
the book for them. We're going to go
ahead and rightclick new block. And
we'll start with a user input block
here. Once we add this user input block,
we can start to add some user inputs. I
will click on this little plus here. And
we will create a new user input. Our
first user input is going to be the book
title. So I'll select short text for the
type. the variable. This is sort of the
little code you're going to call upon
later to pull in this text that they
entered. I'm going to call this book
title for label text. This is what
they're going to see above the text box.
So, we'll just put book title here as
well. And then everything else we can
pretty much leave. So, now I'm going to
come back to my main flow here. Click on
user input again. And we can see we have
the book title user input. Now, I want
them to enter a genre. So, I'm going to
click plus, create new short text
variable, book genre. You'll see what we
do with these variables in just a
minute, so don't get too hung up on this
yet. And then for our label text, once
again, we'll put book genre. And I want
to leave this as a short text field. If
I wanted, I could use a drop down and
have them select a genre, but I want it
to be sort of open-ended. If somebody
wants to put like horror, sci-fi, they
can, right? If you want to put a sort of
blend of genres, I want you to be able
to type that in instead of being limited
to just a drop-down of genres. I'll come
back to our main flow. You can see we've
got our book title, our book genre. Both
are set as required because we will want
both of those to generate everything.
And then the final thing we'll do is a
book description. And this one I will
leave as long text so that they can type
as much as they want into the book
description variable. We'll call it book
description. And then label text book
description. All right. Now, we go back
to our main flow. And I actually don't
want the book description to be
required. So, I'm going to make this
optional. That way, if you leave it
blank, we're going to make AI write the
description for you. So, now we'll go
ahead and connect our nodes. All I have
to do is click on one of these dots
here, drag it to the other node. Now,
these nodes are connected. So, this will
be the first step in our workflow. If I
click on publish here at the top, I can
open my AI agent. And we can see that we
have a simple form that it created for
us. book title, book genre, book
description. Let's put the title Matt's
book, book genre. Fun. And I'll click
next. And our workflow just ends because
we haven't put any other steps in after
that. Now, I want to make it so if they
don't enter a description into the book,
then AI will write the description for
them. I'm going to rightclick, new
block, and for this one, we're going to
generate text. So, we have our generate
text node here. And then we can enter a
prompt right here. And this prompt you
can enter just like you would enter into
any other large language model like chat
GPT or whatever. You can also select
from any model you want. So check this
out. If I open up the models, they
pretty much have like every large
language model you could possibly want
to use. But right now for what we're
doing when it comes to writing, I think
I'm going to stick with GPT5. So we'll
come to OpenAI down here and we will
select GPT5 as the model that we're
going to use. And then we're going to
write our prompt. And for this, we want
it to write a description of what this
book's going to be about. So we'll go
ahead and put write a book description
for a book called. And this is where
we're going to call upon those variables
that we created earlier. So if I do the
little curly brackets and I do two of
them like this, it will actually show
the variables that we had somebody fill
in in that input earlier. Write a book
description for a book called book
title. And we'll pull that in. And then
we also want it to pull in the genre.
So, we'll put in the genre of and I'll
put two curly brackets and we'll pull in
book genre. I do want to give it a
little bit of a guardrail. I don't want
it to go too long on the description.
So, we'll just say make the description
three paragraphs long. And this is the
prompt we're going to send a GPT5 after
somebody uses this input form. Now, I
don't want it to display the description
to me. I actually want this description
to go on to the next step where it
actually starts to write the book. So
for the output behavior here, instead of
displaying it back to me, I want it to
save to a variable. And this will be
another variable that we can call just
like we called on these variables
earlier. So we'll go ahead and call this
book description. So now that we've got
this variable created where it will
generate a book description if we don't
have one, we need to tell our little
tool here when to use that and when not
to. I'm not going to connect this node
yet. I'm going to add a new block here.
We're going to come to view all blocks
and then I'm going to use the logic
block here. So we'll pull in the logic
block right after the user input block.
We'll connect the logic block here. And
then here you basically just describe
what you want to happen. There's no
coding, no extra crazy stuff here. You
just tell it what you want. For the
context, we're going to tell it to look
at book description. So we're telling it
to look at the user input a book
description and decide if it's blank or
has a description already. So we're
basically telling it what this logic
block is going to do. And then condition
one is book description is left blank
and then it says select destination. So
if the book description is left blank,
we'll select our destination. We'll
select generate text. So now if that
book description was left blank. The
logic will see oh it was left blank. We
need to send it to the generate text box
and write a description for it. For our
second condition down here, we'll go
ahead and put there is already a written
description for book description. If you
entered a description here, it will go
on to condition two, but we don't have
anywhere for it to go yet. So the next
thing I want this to do is I wanted to
write a table of contents for our book
based on our either description that the
user input or the one that was generated
here. So, we'll go ahead and click new
block. Generate text. I'm going to use
GPT5 again for this one. And I'm going
to give it this prompt. Come up with 10
chapters for the book titled. And then
we pull in the book title in the genre
of book genre. Here's the description.
The description that was either
generated here or the user input. The
output should just be a list of 10
chapters with their number. And then
here's an example of what I want the
output to look like. And then for output
behavior, once again, we want to save it
to a variable cuz I want it to pass the
chapters to the next step. I don't want
it to display to me yet. And for our
variable name, we'll just call it book
TOC for table of contents. Then we can
go ahead and connect our node here. So
once it writes a description, it comes
down here and writes us a table of
contents based on the book description.
And then we'll go back to our logic
block. And if there is already a book
description written in the user input,
we'll go ahead and just go right here
and bypass our AI generated book
description. I'm going to use a lot of
generate text blocks. So just to keep it
simple in my mind, I'm going to rename
them as I go. So if I right click here,
click rename. I'll call this one
generate TOC. And I will rename this one
generate description. So now we know
what each node does if we're just
looking at this page at a glance. And
one thing I like to do at this point is
sort of pause and make sure things are
working. So I will create a new block
here and then do display content.
Connect our last node to our display
content. And then in the actual message,
I will just put book title like that.
I'm putting the hashtag so it sort of
bolds it and makes it like a header.
We'll put table of contents. And then
we'll pull in the table of contents that
it just generated. Book TOC was the
variable we used. And then we'll just go
ahead and pull in the description as
well. So we can read the description if
an AI generated one. And we'll go ahead
and put book description like that. And
this one I will do display to user.
We're going to actually delete this
node. We're just kind of checking that
everything's working. So, I'll click
publish. We'll go ahead and open the
agent here. And now I'll put book title,
The Wolf in the Woods. Book genre,
fantasy, sci-fi. And then we'll leave
the book description blank because we'll
let AI generate it. So, I'll click next.
And it's just going to go off and do the
work. And we'll actually see right now
it's already on the generate description
step. It used the logic to realize that
it didn't have a description. Now, it's
moved on to the table of contents step.
So, it's generating a table of contents
based on everything we gave it. And then
it sends us to a page with the title,
The Wolf in the Woods. It did give us a
table of contents. It didn't format it
exactly the way I wanted, but that's
okay cuz we're actually passing it as a
variable where we don't actually have to
see it like this, but you can see the
ragged edge of Thornwood is chapter 1.
Chapter 2, Trail of Drowned
Constellations, etc. And then we have
our book description here. So, we know
everything is working so far. Let's do
one last test and actually give it a
description. So this time I'm going to
do book title Charlie's War and then
we'll call it action war. And then for
the description I'm just going to put a
guy named Charlie is going off to war
and he's ready for battle. I just want
to check that the logic does the right
thing. So, if I click next, we'll see,
look, it skipped the generate
description and went straight to
generating a table of contents because
it saw there was a description already.
Perfect. And then here's our
description. Charlie's War, the table of
contents it generated, and then the
description we originally wrote in.
Everything's working great so far. Let's
go ahead and delete this display content
module. That was just a test to make
sure everything was working. Now, what I
want it to do is because we've got a
table of contents, I want it to write
the whole story. But I don't want, you
know, a whole 70,000word book yet. I
just want it to write a description of
every single chapter so that when we go
back through and write it chapter by
chapter, it knows the full story arc.
So, I'm going to go ahead and do a new
block, generate text. I'll rename this
generate story arc. And then over here
in the prompt, I'm using the prompt I'm
writing a book called and then our book
title in the book genre genre. Here is
the description of the book. Here are
the chapters and their titles. So, I'm
feeding it back the table of contents
that we just created. Please write a
description for each chapter. Be
thorough with the description of each
chapter. Include character names,
locations, and what happens in each
chapter. It should fully form into a
complete story that has a clear
beginning, middle, and end. You should
be able to understand the whole story
and how each chapter connects to the
next by reading each chapter
description. And each chapter should
flow into the next. And then I give it a
little description of what I want the
output to look like. Each chapter
description should be on a new line. I
want it to understand the entire story,
the characters, locations they're in,
and all of the plot points of the story
by reading the chapter descriptions. The
idea here is that we build out all 10
chapters and a synopsis of all 10
chapters. And then when I have it write
chapter 1, it knows the whole story arc
as it's writing chapter 1. And then as
it writes chapter 2, it knows the whole
story arc. So as it's writing each
chapter, it knows where the whole story
came from and where it's going. Output
behavior, save it to a variable. We'll
call this chapter descriptions. And then
I'm going to use GPT5. We'll connect
this. And so now after it writes the
table of contents, it's going to go on
to basically write the whole story arc
based on everything we've put in so far.
Title, genre, description, and table of
contents. Once it's got the whole story
arc, then we're going to have it start
writing every single chapter one by one.
And we want this to be a big book. Like
I want it to be a 200page like novel
type book. So I'm going to go ahead and
put new block here. We're going to
generate text and I'm going to rename
this one chapter 1. And then for the
prompt of chapter 1, I'm going to give
it this description. We're writing a
book called book title in the book genre
genre. Here are the chapters and the
description of each chapter. So I just
pulled in the chapter descriptions that
we created here. I don't need to pull in
the full table of contents again because
it's also going to be worked into the
chapter descriptions. And then I put
write chapter 1 in its entirety. The
chapter should be a minimum of 2,000
words and no longer than 5,000 words.
Ensure the book is formatted properly
and tells just the portion of the book
from this chapter. Output behavior saved
a variable variable chapter 1. And then
under model settings, I'm going to stick
with GPT5. We'll use this model. And
then max response size. I'm going to
crank that up a little bit. I want to
make sure that it has enough room to
write a big long chapter. Now, this is
probably way more than we need, but
that'll be fine. And then we can connect
our story arc to chapter 1. So, this
will be the next step in our process
here. And then I'm going to create
chapter 2. We're going to pretty much do
the same thing. I'm going to make a few
slight tweaks to the prompt here. Uh I'm
going to rename this chapter 2. Connect
it over. And then under chapter 2, some
slight variations. Pretty much the same
beginning. We're writing a book. Here's
the chapter descriptions. Everything we
wrote. Write chapter 2 in its entirety.
2,000 to 5,000 words. But then down
here, I put here's chapter 1 in its
entirety so you can continue the story
from where it left off. And then I
brought in chapter 1 that we just wrote
here. So when it writes chapter 2, it
has the entire story line right here in
the chapter description, but it also has
chapter 1. So it knows exactly where
chapter 1 left off before it starts
writing chapter 2. Once again, save to
variable. We'll call this chapter 1.
We'll use GPT5. And crank up our max
response size a little bit. And now it's
a matter of just copying and pasting for
the next eight chapters. So, if I click
on chapter 2 here, rightclick, copy, and
then commandV, I could paste this in
here, rename this one to chapter 3,
connect our nodes, and then down here, I
just need to change a few things. And
I'm just going to do that for the rest.
Now, I'm not going to make you watch me
copy and paste seven more chapters. I'm
just going to use some editing magic.
And we've got all 10 chapters here.
Chapter 4, chapter 5, chapter 6, chapter
7, chapter 8, chapter 9. Don't forget to
change your variable name on each one
here. And finally, chapter 10. I did
make a slight tweak to the prompt here.
Everything's the same for the most part.
But then down here where I wrote write
chapter 10, I put this is the final
chapter of the book. So it should bring
the book to its conclusion. I'm also
going to do a little bit of rearranging
just to kind of keep things on the
screen a little bit. I'll bring chapter
1 down here like this. And let me just
zoom out. And then we'll just kind of
have it sort of weave back and forth so
we can kind of see everything going on
on the screen. I just think it's a
little bit cleaner and easier to keep
track of. We'll zoom back in and now we
can see our full workflow here. So
start, this is where the user inputs
their information. Do we need to write a
description? Yes or no. Then it
generates a table of contents. Then it
generates the entire story arc. Once all
of that is generated, it goes on and
writes chapter 1 all the way through
chapter 10. And the only step we need
now after it does all of this is just to
present the book back to us. And to do
that, I'm going to make a new block and
we're going to display content. We'll
connect our chapter 10. And this time we
will keep it on display to user. For my
message here, I'm just going to plug in
our book title. I put this hashtag here
so that it will make it like a heading.
I'm going to pull in our full table of
contents. This is our original table of
contents that we created here, not the
one with the entire story arc. And then
I just put chapter 1. Pulled in our
variable for chapter 1. Chapter 2 pulled
in our variable for chapter 2 all the
way down to chapter 10. So it's just
going to pull in title, table of
contents, and all of the chapters. And
then under display type, you have some
options. What I found to work with
something this big is to give it back to
me as a Word document. And then I'm
going to put a new block, view all
blocks, and I'm going to tell it this is
where it ends. I'll put our little end
block here to let it know that this is
the finale of our workflow. And it's
done. The whole thing is built. Now, we
can simply click publish, open up our AI
agent here, and we can plug in a book
title, a book genre, and if we want a
book description for a book title, let's
do the winds of winter. If you're not
familiar, that's what the next book in
the Game of Thrones series is supposed
to be called. Let's get it to write it
for us. For book genre, we'll go
fantasy. And then I'll leave the book
description blank. Let the AI come up
with the book description for us. And
then we'll click next. and hands off. We
just let it go. We can see exactly what
step it's on. We could watch it work
through the workflow if we want. It will
take a few minutes. I mean, each one of
these times it is generating a step.
It's going to take a minute or so. So,
this whole thing could take a good 10
minutes to run. Luckily, we have the
power of editing. And here's what our
output looks like. The winds of winter,
our full 10 chapter table of contents,
and then chapter 1, the first black
gale. And then here's our entire chapter
1. Look at this. It's got a pretty long
chapter here. I'm still looking for
chapter 2. All right. Finally, here's
chapter 2. Chapter 2, Brand of the Sky
Trader. And when I actually open this up
in a Word doc, here's what it looks
like. And down at the bottom, we can see
it's 205 pages and 70,000 words. It
wrote a full novel for us. Let's write
one called The Wolf of Fire Wall Street.
And we'll make this one science fiction.
We'll click next. And it will go off and
write our book for us. That's what
agents do. You tell it what you want.
And it just goes and does the thing. And
here's the output. We have a 10 chapter
book called The Wolf of Firewall Street.
Chapter 1, The Opening Bell Blackout.
And we can see we've got some pretty
solid long chapters with some good
dialogue. And I mean, I read through
some of this and it's a very, very
readable, decent book. Let's do one
called Barry Solder and the Magician's
Rock. And for book genre, again, you
could put whatever you want here. So,
let's put young adult fantasy about
child wizards. And let's see what we get
out of this. Here we go. An entire book
called Barry Solder and the Magician's
Rock. All about child wizards. And
ideally, it's a little bit easier to
read cuz it's written for young adults.
Barry Solder can tell what time it was
by the timber of the city. The first
whistle blew low and tired. When the
mills woke, the noon bell was relieved,
etc., etc. I mean, it's definitely a
lower reading level than the previous
books we wrote because we told it it's
for young adults. And so, that is the
entire workflow where you could build an
automation that can write an entire book
for you from scratch. Again, I don't
think people should be going out and
writing books like this. This was more
of me wanting to experiment with Mine
Studio to see if I could do it. This is
more so you can be inspired and see the
types of workflows that you can go build
with Mind Studio if you want. One last
thing we can do is when we're inside of
this workflow, if I click up on the top
here, we can name this novel writing
agent. We'll publish the change up here.
And then when we go back to our various
agents here, we will actually know what
this one is called. The sky is the limit
to the types of automations you can
build with this. This is one of my
favorite things about AI. Now, whatever
type of work you do, you can create
agents and automations and workflows and
just really cool things to make it so
that whatever you're doing becomes a
heck of a lot easier. It just cuts out
some of the steps for you. That's what I
love about Vibe Coding. That's what I
love about these agent workflow
builders. I can find little bottlenecks
in my own business and life and build
little agents to make those things
easier and faster for me. And Mind
Studio is perfect for that kind of
stuff. So, I want to thank them again
for sponsoring this video. And hopefully
you got some ideas, some inspiration of
what else you can do with Mine Studio.
Thank you so much for tuning in and
nerding out with me. This is kind of
more of that like old school tutorial
that I used to make more of. Hoping to
do this type of video more often as
well. So, if you like this kind of
video, you want to see more automations
and workflows and how to build this kind
of stuff, let me know in the comments
and uh I'll be happy to make this kind
of stuff cuz this is a blast for me. So,
thanks again for hanging out. Thanks for
nerding out. Really, really appreciate
you. Hopefully, I'll see you in the next
one. Bye-bye. Thank you so much for
nerding out with me today. If you like
videos like this, make sure to give it a
thumbs up and subscribe to this channel.
I'll make sure more videos like this
show up in your YouTube feed. And if you
haven't already, check out
futuretools.io where I share all the
coolest AI tools and all the latest AI
news. And there's an awesome free
newsletter. Thanks again. Really
appreciate you. See you in the next one.